Guide to the Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, John Gabbert Bowman, Administrative Files, 1921-1945 UA.2.10.1921-1945
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, John Gabbert Bowman, Administrative Files
1921-1945
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Chancellor
UA.2.10.1921-1945
11.8 Linear Feet (21 boxes)
This collection contains the office files of Chancellor Bowman, 1921-1947. In addition to the day to day files of the chancellor's office, there are the files of the financial campaign and construction for building the Cathedral of Learning, the controversy of the Liberal Club and Professor Ralph E. Turner, and Bowmans's correspondence with Helen Clay Frick.
Biography
John Gabbert Bowman became University of Pittsburgh's tenth Chancellor in 1921 and served for 24 years. Prior to coming to the University, he was the president of the State University of Iowa. During his tenure at Pitt, he oversaw the construction of several architecturally beautiful buildings as well as bringing the University into fiscal and academic health.
In spite of opposition from the Board of Trustees and the onset of the Great Depression, he succeeded in securing the resources for the construction of the Cathedral of Learning as well as the Heinz Chapel and the Stephen Foster Memorial. One particular source of support was the construction of the Cathedral's Nationality Rooms by committees comprised of various local ethnic groups from the Pittsburgh area. In addition he toiled to make the Schools of Medicine, Public Health, Social Work, Business and the College academically strong and accredited. The Medical Center came to include eight hospitals and clinics. He built the university from a school of 2300 students to one of 23,000 by the time of his retirement in 1945. The Trustees dedicated the Cathedral of Learning to Bowman on March 9, 1956, the thirtieth anniversary of the breaking of ground for the building.
Upon his retirement, he became the first President and President Honorarius. He died on December 2, 1962 on his farm in Bedford, Pennsylvaina.
Related Material
The University of Iowa holds some official correspondece of Bowman from his years as president.
Arrangement
These files were kept in their original alphabetical order as created by Chancellor Bowman and maintained by his personal secretary Mildred Stegeman.
Acquisition Information
Deposited with the Secretary of the University on April 12, 1965 by Mildred Stegeman, former secretary to Chancellor Bowman. The Secretary to the University deposited this collection in the Archives Service Center upon its establishment in 1968.
Previous Citation
Office file of John G. Bowman.
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, John Gabbert Bowman, Administrative Files, 1921-1945, UA.2.10.1921-1945, University Archives, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains the office files of Chancellor Bowman, 1921-1947. In addition to the day to day files of the chancellor's office, there are the files of the financial campaign and construction for building the Cathedral of Learning, the controversy of the Liberal Club and Professor Ralph E. Turner, and Bowmans's correspondence with Helen Clay Frick.
Access Restrictions
Files in Box 21 are restricted.
Universities and colleges -- Administration -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Records and correspondence; Correspondence; University of Pittsburgh; Administrative records; Bowman, John G. (John Gabbert) -- Records and correspondence; University of Pittsburgh -- Administration; University of Pittsburgh. Chancellor -- Records and correspondence
- Correspondence: A-American Association of University Professors (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Adams, James T. asked by Bowman to write about Pittsburgh and the region, 1939. AAUP and the dismissal of Ralph E. Turner in 1934 (see also folder 137).
- Correspondence: Articles - Unidentified (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Alumni in Hong Kong give dinner in honor of Bowman, August 25, 1938; article on Cathedral naming; "Seven depression years in retrospect"; "What is the spirit of the University of Pittsburgh"; Education in Pittsburgh; "Miracle that we want"; "Teachers Wanted"; "Pittsburgh and the Scientific Spirit"; "Epic Pittsburgh"; "What is my major and why?"
- Correspondence: Association of Urban Universities (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Speech about the Cathedral of Learning, by John G. Bowman at the Annual meeting of the Association of Urban Universities, October 1944; "A singer to pioneers", by John B. Bowman, 1935; The spirit of scientific research, speech at Annual dinner of the Audit Bureau of Circulations, October 7, 1924, by John G. Bowman; Handwritten letter from Dr. Andrey Avinoff to Chancellor Bowman
- Correspondence: Barach - Blumenschein (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Letters from Joseph H. Barach to Dr. John G. Bowman concerning finding a permanent home for the Allegheny County Medical Society, 1930; Bindley Fund for medical research; Correspondence about Native Americans. A book: "Interlinear to Cabeza De Vaca. His relation of the journey from Florida to the Pacific", 1528-1536, by Haneil Long.
- Correspondence: Brackenridge portraits - Brien (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Photographs of the portraits sent to Miss Carol Brackenridge Talbot; Description of the portraits; Blue print of "Transportation" room as proposed for the Cathedral of Learning; Gifts of Mrs. Arthur E. Braun to the French Nationality Room, the 12th floor of the Cathedral of Learning, and books to the Fine Arts Library; "Waterways" showing reproductions of painting of ships
- Correspondence: Bruckner - Byers (Box 1, Folder 6)
  By-laws of the Board of Trustees and ordinances, rules and regulations for the government of the University of Pittsburgh., December 9, 1930; Article on the School of Business Administration; Gift of $500.00 for the French Nationality Room from Mr. & Mrs. J.F. Byers; Building program for area surrounding Cathedral of Learning – John S. Humphreys & J.J. Heffner, architects
- Correspondence: Calhoun - Carnegie Institute of Technology (Box 1, Folder 7)
  California State Department of Education; - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, Early paper of the Foundation, 1935; College athletics and scholarship, 1927; Program for the study of the relations of secondary and higher education, 1928; Carnegie Institute of Technology – letter about a Sanitary Engineering Laboratory; Plans for cooperation; Executive Committee of the Board of Trustees of the two schools; Cooperation between the University and the Pittsburgh Musical Institute, 1931
- Correspondence: Cathedral of Learning publicity (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Articles in several magazines; clippings; letters; and applications for copyright for etching of Cathedral of Learning
- Correspondence: Chalfont - Civic Playhouse (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Letters concerning gifts of money from Miss Eleanor Mc. Chalfont to the School of Medicine; Medal from Charles University in Prague, Czechoslovakia; Chemical warfare service; Letter from C.E.E. Childers from Australia
- Chancellor (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Annual reports, January 1921-28, 1930-32
- Chancellor (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Annual reports 1932-1936
- Charter Day (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Dinner menus; Convocation program, 1930, February; Charter Day Programs, 1924-25; Charter Day address, 1925 "Humanism and Science in the Cathedral of Learning, by John Duncan Spaeth
- Chinese material (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Scrolls sent by Dr. T.L. Yuan of China for the Chinese Memorial Room; Letters of description of the scrolls; Correspondence with Dr. C. Clarence Chu, Embassy of the Republic of China, an alumnus of the University; List of objects sent from China for the room in 1941; In 1941, letter of Chancellor Bowman to Dr. Kung "returned to sender, service suspended"; Letters from the Embassy of the Republic of China with Dr. Clarence Chu, 1943-44; Address of Ambassador, Dr. Hu Shih at dedication of China Memorial Room, October 6, 1939; Dr. Bowman tried to secure a professor to teach Chinese culture and language
- Correspondence: Robert C. Clothier, Dean (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Leaving to become President of Rutgers; Letters concerning Stephen Foster book of songs to be borrowed from Rutgers
- Correspondence: George Hubbard Clapp (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Letters concerning becoming President of the Board of Trustees; Stanton Crawford's letter to Mrs. Mildred Stegeman (who was the secretary to Chancellor Bowman until his death) about the coins which Mr. Clapp gave for display in the Early American Room; Letter from Mrs. Stegeman in which she says that she has cleared out Dr. Bowman's file and "At Dr. Bowman's instructions I am destroying all his personal papers, of course, including any writing he had in the files"; List of items added to the Seismograph Station in 1936; Death notice of George Hubbard Clapp, March 31, 1949; Mr. Clapp's picture painted by Madame Elizabeth Shoumatoff in 1938; Biography of George H. Clapp; 4 pictures of Mr. Clapp; Booklet on coins
- Correspondence: Frederick Mortimer Clapp (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Letters concerning the Fine Arts Department and Miss Frick (see also FF 145)
- Correspondence: Cohen-Commonwealth Fund (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Letters: Coffin Foundation, Mrs. Josiah Cohen, Colwell, Commonwealth Fund.
- Commencement, 1925-1931 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Commencement, 1932-1935 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Commencement, 1936-1938 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Commencement, 1939-1941 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Commencement, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Commencement, 1944-1945 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Commencement, 1946-1947 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Commencement, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Correspondence: Condon - Copernican Quadricennial (Box 4, Folder 26)
  Congress of Women's Clubs Medical; Material on Copernican Quadricentennial; Connely; Condon (Westinghouse)
- Correspondence: Coulson - Day-Klauder (Box 4, Folder 27)
  Cyclotron pamphlet; Bequest to the University by George Liggett Craig in memory of his son, a graduate in 1919; Two letters: architects Day-Klauder and Dr. John Bowman concerning the plans for the Cathedral of Learning in February 1924
- Correspondence: Dice - Dyboski (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Death of Librarian, J. Howard Dice, 1939; Polish refugee, professor Dyboski; Letters Dickson, Dodds, Drerup, Drexel and Duquesne
- Correspondence: Earle - English proficiency (Box 4, Folder 29)
  Dispute between University and the Governor about alumni representatives on the Board of Trustees; Article by Chancellor Bowman about the East Liberty Presbyterian church; Sir Arthur Eddington offered Directorship of Allegheny Observatory, July 1941; Seniors must be proficient in written and spoken English before given full standing; Letters: Eliot, Emeus, Engineering Council, English proficiency
- Correspondence: Erving - Ford (Box 4, Folder 30)
  Gift of Panther and bronze marker by Mrs. Carrie McKay Erving in memory of Roland H. Erving, 1930; Dr. Fessenden's slide rule given to the University, 1945; material and speech used at financial campaign dinner, June 3, 1948; Contrast between 1921 and 1948 for students, faculty, income, when schools added, buildings added and value, etc.; Painting by Emil Foerster of family group given to the University, 1932; Letter from Chancellor Bowman to Henry Ford concerning moving grave of Stephen Foster, 1934; WWI War Dead; Evenng Students Association
- Correspondence: Fountain (Magee) - Frost, Robert (Box 4, Folder 31)
  Christopher L. Magee Memorial Fountain planning with Walker Hancock, artist – for Cathedral of Learning?; Jacobson about Katharine Foulke Scholarship fund (Delta Chapter of Pi Lambda Theta) 1942; Letter from Henry S. Frank when at Lingnan University, Hong Kong in 1940 to Chancellor Bowman; Three horse chestnuts sent to University to plant for Arbor Day by American Forestry Association, 1928; Handwritten letter from Robert Frost to Chancellor Bowman, 1937
- Correspondence: Graper - d'Happart (Box 4, Folder 32)
  Publicity suggestions by Fred Hamlin in November 1940; Letter to Chancellor Bowman, signed, about his collection of manuscripts, letters, etc; Letters: Hambro, Homer, Hamilton (manuscripts), Hance, Hann,
- Correspondence: Herty - Interamerican Affairs (Box 4, Folder 33)
  Letter about landscape painting by George Hetzel which hangs in Alumni Hall, 1937; University sent a paper giving the State policy toward higher education (Pinchot), 1924; John Tasker Howard wrote a book about Ethelbert Nevin; Letters: Moorhead Holland, Hooker, Howard.
- Correspondence: Iowa - Ivanoff (Box 5, Folder 34)
  Chancellor Bowman's honorary degree from Iowa State University, 1935; General Library Building Fund – sale of securities (one was Darlington) 1935. Dr. S.B. Linhart was University secretary
- Correspondence: Jalali-Shirazi - Jessup (Box 5, Folder 35)
  Japanese students war restrictions; letters: Jeffers and Jessup
- Correspondence: John - Kahl (Box 5, Folder 36)
  Programs: Reception honoring Dr. and Mrs. Hugo Kahl, 1941 and Memorial service for him, 1941; Material on the Swedish Nationality Room; Letters: Bob Jones University, Illustrated letter from Mrs. Walton John
- Correspondence: Edgar Jonas Kaufmann (Box 5, Folder 37)
  Honorary Degree and est. of Emma Kaufmann Clinic
- Correspondence: Kellogg Foundation (Box 5, Folder 38)
  Scholarships to Medical and Nursing students, 1942; Grants to medical school 1942; Hugh Thomsom Kerr's letters to Chancellor Bowman during his illness; Dr. Kerr to be a University Trustee
- Correspondence: Kidd - Klimcheck (Box 5, Folder 39)
  Howard Kidd's remarks about Chancellor Bowman's character; Plans for a Transportation Room in the Cathedral of Learning; Mr. A.A. Klimcheck's memos concerning the building of the Cathedral and Nationality Rooms, 1939; Klauder's note of thanks for receipt of silver medal of Cathedral of Learning.
- Correspondence: Kokotsis - Littlefield (Box 5, Folder 40)
  Letter in which the painter Mr. Koktsis gives one of his Greek landscape paintings to Chancellor Bowman; He painted Dr. Bowman's picture; Correspondence with Zing Yan Kuo, Representative of the Chinese Government on Education; Article: "The symbol of a city," by Charles F. Lewis
- Correspondence: Josiah Kirby Lilly, 1931-1934 (Box 5, Folder 41)
- Correspondence: Josiah Kirby Lilly, 1935-1937 (Box 5, Folder 42)
- Correspondence: Josiah Kirby Lilly, 1938-1941 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- Correspondence: Josiah Kirby Lilly, 1942-1948 (Box 5, Folder 44)
- Correspondence: Samuel Black Linhart (Box 6, Folder 45)
  Secretary of the University from 1906 until his retirement June 30, 1936; Biographical clippings from Linhart's death, December 11, 1936; Letter explaining Lockhart Trust Fund payments to the University
- Correspondence: Locke - McMasters (Box 6, Folder 46)
  Otto Helmold Memorial Fund, 1941; $2000 given to Dr. H.E. Longenecker by Nutrition Foundation, Inc. to study "Availability of fatty acids in hydrogenated fats", 1943; History of glass in Pittsburgh district, written by Dr. A.S. Silverman in 1944 at the request of Dr. H.E. Longenecker; Dr. Herbert E. Longenecker became a member of the Food and Nutrition Board of the National Research Council, 1943; Contract for study of fats, 1942; Letters: Lord Halifax; Ludewig, Luther from Decca Records, Mackay, Macleod.
- Correspondence: Mandexter - Martin (Governor) (Box 6, Folder 47)
  Bequest of picture (Rembrandt's anatomy Lecture)painted by Charles Heberer (copy of Rembrandt's "Anatomy Lecture") by Thomas M. Marshall, Jr., 1944; Markle Foundation support for King's, Biochemistry of Bone Marrow, 1942; Letters: Elder Marshall, Edward Martin, William Martin,
- Correspondence: Albert Mansbridge (Box 6, Folder 48)
  Letters concerning the English Nationality Room, 1934
- Correspondence: Mayo - McEllroy (Box 6, Folder 49)
  Dr. Phillip Hench on Bowman's retirement; picture of Dr. and Mrs. Mayo; Letters: Chancellor McCormick; Bulletin from the burial service of Dr. S.B. McCormick; Speech of Dr. William J. Holland at the burial service; Dr. L.G. Beinhauer established fund "Dermatological Research Fund"; Mrs. Hugh Patton makes a donation for cancer research,1944; James S. Kemper Foundation fellowship in Industrial Medicine; Beaumont Trust support of the Laboratory of Experimental Endocrinology; Arrangements made to have Mr. Malcolm Parcell paint the portrait of Dr. James Bissett Murdoch, the first Dean of the Medical School; Letter from Sarah Mellon Scaife to William S. McEllroy, Dean of the School of Medicine regarding the building of a cyclotron, 1940; Donation from J.B. Orr for cancer research; Dr. McEllroy correspondence concerning gifts for the Medical School; Commencement program for School of Medicine, 1944.
- Correspondence: McKay - Medical Center (Box 6, Folder 50)
  McKay appointed member of the Civil Service Commission of Pittsburgh; Letter of gifts; Memo from Agnes Starrett re; McMasters family's four generations of graduates; List of purchase of bonds for the Stadium, 1925; Form for Agreement for Nurses' Residence between University and five hospitals; Starting building fund; Federal fund for hospital construction, 1945; School of Nursing: Institute on the health problems of returning veteran, 1945; Bellefield boiler, costs to accommodate hospitals and Upper campus buildings, 1945; Medical Center: summary of investment in buildings, grounds, equipment and Endowment and bed capacity, January 1, 1945; History of its beginnings; Agreement between Children's hospital and the University of Pittsburgh, 1926; Need for a Nurses' Residence; Bequest by Mrs. T.N. Miller for a "Woman's Hospital" in 1897; Requesting Miller Fund Trustees if money can be used in Medical Center project; Explanation of provisional plan for Miller Hospital in Medical Center, by R.R. Huggins, Dean of the Medical School; Report of Charles L. Wooldridge, Inc. Consulting engineers on the procedure to start building Medical Center
- Correspondence: Andrew W. Mellon (Box 6, Folder 51)
  Biography; Correspondence concerning the Cathedral of Learning, Veterans Hospital, Mellon Institute. Purchase of "Frick Acres" (14 acres for the Cathedral of Learning; university debts
- Correspondence: A. W. Mellon Educational and Charitable Trust (Box 52)
- Paul Mellon and Richard Beatty Mellon (Box 52, Folder 53)
  Letters and Biographies; Obituary, 1933; Bibles given to Carnegie Public Library June 1908; Cathedral of Learning
- Mellon Institute, documents and pamphlets (Box 52, Folder 54)
  Pamphlets on the Institute; Dedication booklet, 1937; Agreement with University of Pittsburgh, 1928 and 1940; Old Mellon Institute transferred to University of Pittsburgh, 193?; Andrew Mellon and the Mellon Institute
- Correspondence: Mesta Machine - Mitchell, A.E. (Box 52, Folder 55)
  Letters: Mesta Scholarship, Metcalf, Minno, A.E. Mitchell
- Correspondence: Ruth Crawford Mitchell (Box 7, Folder 56)
  Material on Irish Nationality Room – planning, 1944; Lecture series proposed, 1942-44; Egyptian Room proposed; Material on Chinese Room; Planning for English Room; proposal for Lithuanian Room; Material on the Czechoslovak Room 1929; Letter re: several Nationality Classrooms; Draft of "Teacher's Wanted"
- Programs and correspondence: Ruth Crawford Mitchell (Box 7, Folder 58)
  Some correspondence; Nationality Committee programs; Chancellor Bowman's material for the program of the Copernican Quadricentennial, 1943; two published articles by William Hung.
- Correspondence: William W. Morrell (Box 7, Folder 58)
  University editor 1926-1930; Biography; Letters to and from Chancellor Bowman; Clippings of his work with the Miami Herald as "Hugh Hough"
- Correspondence: Morgan - Murray (Box 7, Folder 59)
  Gifts from Edmund W. Mudge, 1934; Mulert Memorial Room for late Justus Mulert Dedication program, 1942; Will of Mr. Mulert; Correspondence with John Murray, President of the University College of the South West, Exeter England 1932-40; Letters: Morton, Mount Union College; John Murray
- Nationality Rooms book (Box 7, Folder 60)
  List of those receiving the book; Thank you notes, 1947-48
- Correspondence: Nevin - North American Review (Box 7, Folder 61)
  Letters by Mrs. Mildred Stegeman to Dr. Theodore Finney (Music Department) in which she says that all Ethelbert Nevin material and manuscripts were sent to Dr. Finney for the Nevin memorial Room, January 7, 1930; F.F. Nicola about land on corner of Forbes and Park, 1928; Letter from Chancellor Bowman to Mr. Nicola, 1930; Report on the proposed building for University of Pittsburgh, March 18, 1926, by Henry Lee Norris of Columbia University, Department of buildings and grounds – report requested by Andrew W. Mellon
- Correspondence: O'Connell - Orr, Louis (Box 7, Folder 62)
  Letters regarding tracing a Gold Medal written about in a letter to Col. Henry Bouquet which General Forbes wanted to give to his men, 1759; Omicron Delta Kappa, Gamma Circle invited Chancellor Bowman and Dr. Linhart to membership; (Gamma Circle founded in 1916); Both accepted, 1927; Membership open to students in junior and senior classes on basis of distinction in scholarship, athletics, and student activities; Thanksgiving Open House program, November 28, 1948; Louis Orr etchings of the interior of the Cathedral of Learning; Letters from Mr. Orr; Made 200 artist's proof etchings of the Cathedral of Learning 17" x 22" – copyright in name of University; Etched copper plate to be destroyed 1937; Louis Orr (home address in Paris)
- Correspondence: Paderewski - Parry (Box 7, Folder 63)
  University has the original MS. Of the opera, Manru of Ignace Paderewski; List of paintings of faculty and officers and their locations and sizes; correspondece and programs about Pardue
- Correspondence and documents: Pennsylvania Federation of Women's Clubs - Peterson (Box 7, Folder 64)
  Clubwoman article by Bowman, "Character in Education"; Pennsylvania Scotch-Irish Society – Chancellor Bowman spoke at meeting March 22, 1929; Pennsylvania Society – Chancellor spoke at meeting December 15, 1934; Handwritten letter from George Wharton Pepper to Chancellor Bowman – George Wharton Pepper prize and list of awardees 1922-31; Peterson, "The Greatest Enterprise of Pittsburgh", by George W. Pepper; Edwin L. – Short story classes (clipping); Poem "Chinese Angler"
- Correspondence and documents: Pittsburgh Foundation - Pittsburgh College of Pharmacy (Box 7, Folder 65)
  Pittsburgh College of Pharmacy bemerged with Western University of Pennsylvania; Pittsburgh Free Dispensary
- Correspondence: Posner Table - Quick (Box 8, Folder 66)
  Mr. & Mrs. Henry Posner donated Louis XV table to the University in 1947 which was to be in Women's activities room on the 12th floor of the Cathedral of Learning;; Scientific research as first aid to right advertising, by John Gabbert Bowman (In Printers' Ink, 1924); Psychiatric Hospital – gave land for hospital – copy of deed, 1932; Queen Marie of Romania
- Radio Studio at Pitt (Box 8, Folder 67)
  Radio talks 1925-1936 by Chancellor Bowman; Address: Hamilton Stewart – "The most interesting city in the world" 1925; First anniversary of the University of Pittsburgh Radio Studio of station KDKA (Radio publication no. 14), 1925; Chancellor Bowman's speech at the opening of the station, March 31, 1924; "Story of the Educational Radio Studio" (Radio Publication no. 3)
- Correspondence: Reed - Retail Training (Box 8, Folder 68)
  Bureau for Retail Training, 1926-41: agreements of list of stores to support Bureau
- Correspondence: Richardson - Rudd (Box 8, Folder 69)
  Darlington Estate: Elizabeth Darlington Richardson made claim for payment she said due her from the estate, 1928; Edwin Rudd gift for the Scandinavian Room
- Correspondence: G. Stanley Rupp (Box 8, Folder 70, Folder 70a)